L. D. Warren Papers
L. D. Warren Papers
1952-1968
1966-1968
Warren, Leonard Deakyne, 1906-1992.
2 linear ft.
44 original editorial cartoons, 1 reproduction and biographical clippings.
2651181
Biographical History
Leonard D. Warren (1906-1992) commonly known as L.D. Warren was an American editorial cartoonist.
Leonard Deakyne “L. D.” Warren was born on December 27, 1906 in Wilmington, Delaware and graduated from Camden High School in Camden, New Jersey. Warren took a job with the New Jersey Courier Post and in 1927 left for the Philadelphia Record where he drew feature, sports and editorial cartoons. Warren also worked on a strip featuring the character Penny Penguin for the Gulf Oil Corporation in the 1930s and contributed to Gulf Funny Weekly during that time.
After twenty years with the Record, Warren became the editorial cartoonist for the Cincinnati Enquirer in 1947. While at the Enquirer, his work was also syndicated through the McNaught Syndicate from 1951 to 1974.
In 1954, Warren’s work was included in a cartoon exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art and exhibited at the National Portrait Gallery in London. Warren's artwork also appeared with an American Association of Editorial Cartoonists show in Yugoslavia. He taught cartooning as a guest instructor at the Art Academy of Cincinnati and gave chalk talks to University of Cincinnati students. His work was used to illustrate books, magazines and brochures.
Warren received several awards from the Freedoms Foundation, the National Headliner award in 1961 and was nominated for the National Cartoonists Society Reuben award three times. The book, The World and Warren’s Cartoons was published in 1977.
In 1973, Warren retired from the Cincinnati Enquirer but continued to contribute a weekly cartoon to the newspaper. He recommended cartoonist Jim Borgman to be his replacement.
L.D. Warren died on May 14, 1992.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The L. D. Warren Papers are comprised of Cartoons and Clippings.
Cartoons make up the bulk of the collection. There are 44 original editorial cartoons drawn for the Cincinnati Enquirer from 1966 through 1968 and one reproduction of a cartoon that was published March 1, 1952. Warren’s cartoons were known to closely match the conservative views on the Enquirer’s editorial page. These cartoons focus on national and international issues. There are no cartoons representing local affairs. The subjects depicted include the 1968 presidential election primary candidates, government spending and the Vietnam War. Worth noting is that Warren frequently used animals to represent people and concepts.
Original cartoons measure 14" x 22 1/2" with an image size of approximately 10" x 12" and were drawn with ink and crayon on textured paper. Captions appear in ink. Blue pencil was used for borders, dates and size information. Other notations appear in red pencil.
Clippings (1966-1968) contains one folder of articles about Warren and his work including articles featuring some of his best cartoons. The articles appeared in the Cincinnati Enquirer and the Sunday Cincinnati Pictorial Enquirer.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in chronological order. Clippings are arranged in alphabetical order by article title.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Warren, Leonard Deakyne, 1906-1992.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cincinnati enquirer.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Cincinnati (Ohio); Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Cincinnati (Ohio); Expenditures, Public -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Elections -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Cincinnati (Ohio); World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of L. D. Warren, 1967-1969.
The reproduction of the 1952 cartoon is of unknown provenance.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 45 items
  - 1952 Mar 1, reproduction on paper; 6 3/4" x 9" (Oversize 1)
    "Bull Dogs": elections
  - 1966, 14 1/4" x 22 ½" (Oversize 1)
    Jan 1: "Daddy"- social security, taxes, Lyndon B. Johnson
    Jan 4: "This is Our Newly Decorated Bridal Suite!": draft
    Jan 24: "Woman's Work is Never Done": India, Nehru Gandhi, China
    Feb 1: "Pool- Anyone?": peace, Vietnam War
    Feb 8: "Show me a state's right that delivers the vote and I'll eat my hat!": Lyndon B. Johnson, unions
    Feb 25: "I guess he wants to be sure he's safe on first!": France, Charles De Gaulle, NATO
    Apr 30: "Unfair! I thought he was the father!": New York City, unions, newspapers
    May 9: "Not so fast, Lurleen! Don't forget, I still wear the pants around here!": George Wallace, Lurleen Wallace
    May 12: "They're not running, they're thinking out in front of the president!- Schlesinger": Robert F. Kennedy, Ted Kennedy
    Jun 8: "Let's talk this over- what do you have in mind?": Buddhists, Vietnam War
    Jun 10: "Class of '66": graduates
    Jul 18: "Hmmf! No wonder she can't keep her slip from showing!": Romania, Warsaw Pact, NATO, France
    Oct 25: "He does! Don't you, honey?": food prices, boycotts
    Nov 18: "Holy zodiac! I never had to follow an act like that at the Parthenon!": space exploration
    Dec 15: "Silent Night": Middle East
  - 1967, 14 1/4" x 22 ½" (Oversize 1)
    Jan 11: "Come on in- the water's fine!": Rhodesia, Lyndon B. Johnson, Harold Wilson
    Jan 24: "Just don't get the idea it's magic": Jordan, Middle East, weapons
    Feb 20: "We will cross that bridge when we get to it": Indira Ghandi
    Feb 22: "Faith of our fathers living still": George Washington, religion
    Mar 7: "Sorry about that, Adam!": Adam Clayton Powell, Jr.
    Mar 31: "The Opaque Curtain": Supreme Court
    Apr 5: "It isn't raining rain, you know- it's raining volunteers": Lyndon B. Johnson, labor, economy, emergency strike legislation
    Jun 20: "What did you have tin mind, Harold?": common market, Charles De Gaulle, Harold Wilson
    Jul 6: "The land of milk and honey": (vulture overlooks a group of people, possibly refugees)
    Aug 24: "Shh! Johnny! Do you want everybody to think we're lost?": foreign aid
    Aug 31: "It only hurts for a little while!": Korean War, taxes, Vietnam War, World War II, Lyndon B. Johnson
    Oct 9: "You've Got the whole world in your hands": National Newspaper Week
    Oct 10: "When a fellow needs a friend": Vietnam War, Lyndon B. Johnson
    Oct 17: "Just Remember! No haircut!!": Congress, Lyndon B. Johnson, government spending
    Nov 8: "This should help us make up our minds!": elections, Ronald Reagan, Nelson Rockefeller, George W. Romney, Richard Nixon
  - 1968, 14 1/4" x 22 ½" (Oversize 1)
    Jan 5: "I've never skated before, hold me tight!": U.S. Dollar
    Jan 8: "Let me have one five and one one, please!": Republican Party, Democratic Party, Franklin D. Roosevelt, George Washington
    Jan 30: "Happy Tet!": Vietnam War
    Feb 19: "All those in favor raise their right hands!": Supreme Court, crime
    Feb 20: "It's hard to believe, Mr. President, but stalactites grow at the rate of only an inch a year!": Vietnam War, peace
    Mar 8: "I have the same problem, young man- he never changes medicine, only larger doses!": Harold Wilson, Lyndon B. Johnson, socialized medicine, health care
    Apr 11: "Where did we got wrong?": Vietnam War, Lyndon B. Johnson, demonstrations
    Apr 12: "On a hill far away stood an old rugged cross"
    Apr 29: "It must be later than we think!": Robert F. Kennedy, Eugene McCarthy, Hubert Humphrey
    May 3: "She Loves Me! I knew I'd find one if I searched long enough!": Nelson Rockefeller, Republican Party
    May 23: "Dirty French post cards, Monsieur?": Communism, Charles De Gaulle, strikes
    Jun 20: "The Difference is they get paid for not growing!": farming, hunger
    Jun 21: "It's your move!": Vietnam War, peace, Ho Chi Minh
    Sep 27: "But a Mr. Warren made my reservation last June!": Abe Fortas, Supreme Court, Congress
    Nov 11: "That looks great! Stop right there, Gene!": Eugene McCarthy, Hubert Humphrey, Lyndon B. Johnson
- Clippings
  - "Editorial Cartoonist L.D. Warren as He Sees the World / As His Wife Sees Him Cincinnati Pictorial Enquirer, 2 Jan 1966 (Oversize 1)
  - "Best of L.D." Cincinnati Pictorial Enquirer, 1 Jan 1967 (Oversize 1)
  - "The First 20 Years" Cincinnati Pictorial Enquirer, 13 Aug 1967 (Oversize 1)
  - L.D. Warren's 10 Best- Cincinnati Pictorial Enquirer, 29 Dec 1968 (Oversize 1)
  - "L.D. Warren's Cartoons Placed in Public Library" Cincinnati Enquirer, 3 Feb 1966 (Oversize 1)